

Shantanu Kumar Rahut

Nationality: Bangladeshi

(+49) 15753950026

Date of birth: 10/12/1995

Gender: Male

■ Email address: shantanurahut@gmail.com

• Address: Scheidterstraße 259, Top Floor, Room No: 7, 66125 Saarbrücken (Germany

)

ABOUT ME

I am a researcher by passion and want to take software development as my profession. I enjoy reading, learning, and talking about computers, fantasy, and philosophy. I am an ambivert as a person. Persistence and dedication are my strong suit.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Backend Developer

natif.ai [01/08/2021 - 31/01/2022]

City: Saarbrücken Country: Germany

I worked as a backend developer (work student) for my company. I worked on API development under the guidance and supervision of my team lead. I mostly worked with python. My job responsibility included but was not limited to - creating new endpoints in the API to add new features, modifying current endpoints of the API to add new features, fixing bugs, and writing tests. For working on API I mostly used FastAPI, and for writing tests I mostly used pytest.

Software Development Intern

TwiHive Digital [10/11/2020 - 10/02/2021]

City: Lisbon

Country: Portugal

TwiHive Digital is a startup company. I worked here remotely on a no-salary basis to gain experience. I was assigned a solo project where I worked with python(Pillow). After my internship period was over, the company offered me a flexible work hour - no salary-based position.

Teaching Assistant

East West University [09/2017 – 08/2019]

City: Dhaka

Country: Bangladesh

I worked as a Teaching Assistant at my University (from where I did my B.Sc.). I used to help my professor in taking lab classes, tutorial classes, making study materials, and grading answer sheets.

Intern

Microsoft Bangladesh [02/2018 - 10/2018]

City: Dhaka

Country: Bangladesh

I did this internship under **Microsoft Bangladesh-Young Bangla Internship Program.** I, along with my teammates created a Bengali Hate Speech classification model while doing the internship. I received no salary, and I did this internship to gain experience.

Mentor [python]

EWU Robotics Club [03/2018 - 12/2018]

City: Dhaka

Country: Bangladesh

I worked with my university robotics club as a Mentor for python.

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

M.Sc. in Data Science and Artificial Intelligence

Saarland University [15/03/2021 - Current]

Address: 66123 Saarbrücken (Germany)

https://www.uni-saarland.de/

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering

East West University [15/01/2015 - 18/12/2018]

Address: Jahurul Islam City Gate, A/2 Jahurul Islam Ave, 1212 Dhaka (Bangladesh)

https://www.ewubd.edu/

Higher Secondary Certificate

Khilgaon Government High School [01/07/2011 - 03/08/2013]

Address: Khilgaon, 1219 Dhaka (Bangladesh)

http://www.khilgaonghs.edu.bd/

Secondary School Certificate

Khilgaon Government High School [01/01/2001 - 12/05/2011]

Address: Khilgaon, 1219 Dhaka (Bangladesh)

http://www.khilgaonghs.edu.bd/

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): Bengali

Other language(s):

English

LISTENING C2 READING C2 WRITING B2

SPOKEN PRODUCTION B2 SPOKEN INTERACTION B2

DIGITAL SKILLS

Software Development / Machine Learning / Python / C++ / C / HTML / CSS / SQL / JavaScript / Git / Object-Oriented Programming / Github / Web Development / FastAPI / pytest

PUBLICATIONS

Scientific Paper Peer-Reviewing System With Blockchain, IPFS, and Smart Contract [2019]

https://www.igi-global.com/gateway/chapter/230197

Automatic Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia Detection and Comparative Analysis from Images [2019]

https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8820299

Bengali Spoken Digit Classification: A Deep Learning Approach Using Convolutional Neural Network

[2020]

https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877050920311273?via=ihub

Bengali Abusive Speech Classification: A Transfer Learning Approach Using VGG-16

[2020]

https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/9350919

DJournal: A blockchain based scientific paper reviewing system with self- adaptive reviewer selection sub-system

[2021]

https://www.igi-global.com/gateway/chapter/280825

PROJECTS

Three-in-a-row

It is a version of the famous game connect-four. I have implemented machine learning using reinforcement learning(Q-Learning). it was a project for my Artificial Intelligence course at my university. I wrote the program in C++.

GitHub Link: https://github.com/p0l4r/Three-In-A-Row

Toxic comment classification

This model classifies Toxic(Hateful) or Nontoxic (Not hateful) online comments. The data set used in this program can be found in Kaggle. I wrote the program in python.

GitHub Link: https://github.com/p0l4r/Toxic-comment-classification

Matrix factorization based collaborative filtering

Metrix-factorization is a lightweight program written in python language for performing basic operations for matrix factorization-based collaborative filtering. I have plans to create a python module from this repository in the future.

GitHub Link: https://github.com/p0l4r/Matrix-Factorization---based-Collaborative-Filtering

Pdf to audiobook converter

A simple program for converting pdf to audio, written in python language.

GitHub Link: https://github.com/p0l4r/PDF-to-AudioBook

Calculator

Simple calculator, written in C#.

GitHub Link: https://github.com/p0l4r/Calculator-By-Shantanu

CGPA calculator for EWU

A simple app for calculating CGPA of EWU, BD; using C#.

GitHub Link: https://github.com/p0l4r/CGPA-calculator-by-shantanu

Guess the number

A simple Guess The Number game using C#.

GitHub Link: https://github.com/p0l4r/Guess-The-Number

HONOURS AND AWARDS

Merit Scholarship

East West University [2018]

Merit Scholarship holder (Awarded by the East West University).

Champion of Idea War

EWU Telecommunication Club [2016]

Champion of Idea War (Telco Warfare-2016)

ORGANISATIONAL SKILLS

Core member of organization committee

I was a core member of the organization committee and organized 20 years celebration of the EWU CSE department. I was in charge of the Decoration team.

PERSONAL PROFILE LINKS

Google Scholar Profile

https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=gShhZBUAAAAJ&hl=en

ResearchGate Profile

https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Shantanu-Rahut

GitHub Profile

https://github.com/p0l4r

GitLab Profile

https://gitlab.com/p0l4r